<document>
   <properties>
      <title>Services for J2EE applications</title>
      <author >Jorge Ferrer</author>
   </properties>
   <body>
      <section name="Services for J2EE applications">
         <p>
         	EasyConf offers some services useful when developing J2EE applications.
            All services are implemented both as a <i>Servlet</i> and as a
            <i>Struts action</i>.
			</p>
         <p>
            To have access to the Servlet services it is necessary to add the
            necessary configuration to the <tt>web.xml</tt> file of the application.
            It is strongly recommended that the apropriate permisions are specified
            to prevent unauthorized access to these services.
         </p>
         <p>
            To have access to the Struts Action services it is necessary to add 
            a mapping to the <tt>struts.xml</tt> file of the application.
         </p>
         <p>
            Currently there is only one service, the refresh configuration service.
         </p>
      </section>
      <section name="Refresh configuration service">
         <p>
        		Manually refresh the configuration of either one specific component 
            or all the configuration components. This service can receive one
            parameter: <tt>componentName</tt>. If a parameter with that name is
            found it's configuration will be removed from the cache. If it does
            not existe the command is ignored.            
         </p>         
         <p>
            If no parameter called <tt>componentName</tt> is found, all configurations
            will be deleted from the cache.
         </p>
         <p>
            Note this service will delete cache entries and the 
            configuration will actually be reloaded on a one by one basis
            the next time the applications asks for the configuration of
            some component.
         </p>
         <p>
            <b>Controlling the output</b>
            <ul>
               <li><b>Struts action</b>: The struts action returns <tt>SUCCESS</tt> as 
               a forward always. It is left to you to create the JSP page that will create the
               HTML to be returned to the user when this action is called.</li>
               <li><b>Servlet</b>: The servlet returns a very basic HTML response to the user
                  with a message in english. You can modify this response by subclassing
                  the servlet and overriding the method
                  <tt>writeSuccessResponse(HttpServletResponse response, String componentName)</tt></li>
            </ul>
         </p>
      </section>
   </body>
</document>