<document>

  <properties>
    <title>Welcome to EasyConf</title>
    <author email="jorge.ferrer  gmail.com">Jorge Ferrer</author>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="What is EasyConf?">
      <p>
        EasyConf is a library to access configuration of software components and 
        applications. It defines simple conventions to make it easier to use. It 
        was born in a portlets-based portal and has several features useful for 
        this and similar environments.
      </p>
      <p>
        EasyConf aims to make very easy to make Java applications configurable. You can start
        with a very simple scheme and when
        you need it you'll be able to add powerful functionality such as XML files, support for 
        several environments or aggregation of componentes.
      </p>
    </section>
    <section name="State">
      <p>
        EasyConf is stable and <i>production ready</i>. It is being used in several production 
        environments without any known bugs. EasyConf is based on several <a href="dependencies.html">external libraries</a>
        which are also stable.
      </p>
      <p>
        Version number has not reached 1.0 yet because we are currently waiting for feedback from
        the community about the <a href="reference/conventions.html">conventions used</a>. Based on this 
        feedback some of the current conventions may change. Should that happen, changes needed when 
        updating will be clearly documented.
      </p>
    </section>
    <section name="Main features">
      <p>
	  The key <a href="user/features.html">features</a> of EasyConf are:
	  <ol>
	    <li><b>Usage of easy to remember conventions</b> to simplify configuring
	      applications</li>
	    <li><b>Component based configuration</b> (for example for portlets
	      and portals)</li>
	    <li><b>Support for multiple environments</b> (development, integration,
  preproduction, production, etc)</li>
        <li><b>Support for <i>typed</i> property files, XML files or a combination of both</b></li>
	  </ol>
      </p>

      </section>
    </body>
  </document>