<document>
   <properties>
      <title>Roadmap</title>
      <author >Jorge Ferrer</author>
   </properties>
   <body>
      <section name="Roadmap">
         <p>
            After its release under an open source license the main purpose of
            its developers is to receive feedback on its conventions. Once
            those conventions are consolidated version 1.0 will be released
         </p>
         <p>
            Meanwhile we have several features in mind. We expect most
            of them to be finished in the first half of 2005.
         </p>
      </section>
      <section name="Planned features">
         <p>
            <b>Planned features for property files</b>
         </p>
         <ul>
            <li>Reloading (done in version 0.9.0)</li>
            <li>Properties in database (beta implementation in version 0.9.0)</li>
            <li>Properties in JNDI (beta implementation in version 0.9.0)</li>
            <li>New property types: name-value pairs, locale, dates, etc.</li>
          </ul>   
         <p>
            <b>Planned features for XML files</b>
         </p>
         <p>The first planned features are to solve the currently known
            limitations of the support of XML files with respect to
            the configuration through property files. These are:
         </p>
         <ul>
            <li>You can only have one XML file per component</li>
            <li>There is no complete support for changing XML configuration
            when aggregating components. Only that offered by variables</li>
            <li>There is no complete support for changing XML configuration
            for each differnt environment. Only that offered by variables.</li>
         </ul>
         <p>
            Other planned features for XML files are:
         </p>
         <ul>
            <li>Storage of XML files in a database</li>
            <li>Reloading (done in version 0.9.0)</li>
         </ul>
         <p>
           <b>Finish the reload configuration service (done in version 0.9.0)</b>
         </p>
         <p>
            Implement the servlet interface and fix it by including
            Jakarta Commons Configuration v1.1 when it is released (done in version 0.9.0).
         </p>
         <p>
           <b>Leverage JMX technology</b> (access and modification of configuration through
           JMX is already available in version 0.9.0, more will come)
         </p>
      </section>
   </body>
</document>