<document>
   <properties>
      <title>Property filters</title>
      <author >Jorge Ferrer</author>
   </properties>
   <body>
      <section name="What are property filters?">
         <p>
            Filters are a method to give several values to a property and choose one of 
            them based on the value of one or more selectors. They have been found particularly
            useful in environments which have heavy personalization requirements, although
            thay can be very handy in a lot of other situations
         </p>
         <p>
				As an example will take a property called <tt>skin</tt> which defines the default
            skin of a user in an educative portal. The users are categorized in types
            differentiating teachers from students from others. The students are further 
            subdivided depending on their grade level (primary, secondary, etc). We 
            want to let the person
            configuring the portal set a different default skin depending on the type of 
            user. To do this we retrieve the property value using the user type and
            subtype as selectors:
			</p>
         <source>
            getProperties().getString("skin", Filter.by(userType, userSubtype));
         </source>
         <p>
            In the properties file the skin property may be given different values
            depending of the values of the user type and subtype. For example:
         </p>
         <source>
            skin[teacher]=blue
            skin[student][secundary]=green
            skin[student]=yellow
            skin=grey
         </source>
         <p>
            With this configuration the default skin is <i>grey</i> and it will 
            be applied to users which
            are not teachers neither students. For students the default skin is
            <i>yellow</i> unless it is of subtype secundary in which case the
            default skin will be <i>green</i>.
         </p>
         <p>
            EasyConf supports an unlimited number of selectors. They can be optionally 
            used in any of the supported property types with or without a defautl value.
            Check the <a href="/apidocs/com/germinus/easyconf/Filter.html">Javadoc of 
               the Filter class</a> for more information
         </p>
      </section>
   </body>
</document>